Guide to the Center for Constitutional Rights Records TAM.589
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Center for Constitutional Rights Records
1959-2010
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Center for Constitutional Rights (New York, N.Y.)
TAM.589
240.5 Linear Feet in 234 record cartons and 13 manuscript boxes
6 websites in 6 archived websites.
The Center for Constitutional Rights (CCR) is a non-profit legal advocacy organization based in New York City. The Center was initially established to provide legal services and financial support to lawyers representing civil rights movement activists in Mississippi, but has since broaded its focus to civil liberties and human rights activism and litigation more generally. This unprocessed collection of records created or collected by CCR consists of correspondence, political ephemera, newspaper clippings, websites, research files, and legal documents, including briefs, motions, and trial transcripts documenting the organization's legal advocacy.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials in this collection include those protected by attorney-client privilege and/or containing personally identifiable information. Restricted materials are located in the following boxes: 67, 143, 174, 179-183, 185-246.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were transferred from New York Public Library's Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture in 2012; additional materials were also donated in 2012.
http://www.ccr-ny.org/v2/home.asp was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Other Left Activism Web Archive. http://www.ccrjustice.org/ was added in 2008. http://ccrjustice.org/cases-issue was added in 2009 as part of the Guantanamo Bay Detention Camp & War Crimes (U.S.) Web Archive. https://ccrjustice.org/home/what-we-do/active-cases was added in 2015. In 2015, these website were migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2020, https://www.alecattacks.org/ was added to the Other Left Activism Web Archive. The accession number associated with this website is 2020.032. In December 2020, https://www.foiabasics.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2021.059. In September 2021, https://docs.google.com/document/d/176Yds1p63Q3iaKilw0luChMzlJhODdiPvF2I4g9eIXo/edit was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2022.014.
Appraisal
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The order in which these materials were sent to the Tamiment Library has been maintained.
Historical Note
The Center for Constitutional Rights (CCR) is a non-profit legal advocacy organization based on New York City. It was founded in 1966 by civil rights lawyers and legal activists, including William Kuntsler, Morton Stavis, Arthur Kinoy, and Ben Smith. The Center was initially established to provide legal services and financial support to lawyers representing civil rights movement activists in Mississippi. Since then, CCR has broadened its focus to civil liberties and human rights activism and litigation more generally, providing legal assistance to a variety of clients, including Guantanamo Bay detainment camp prisoners and victims of racial profiling in the wake of 9/11.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Archival Materials
National Lawyers Guild Records (TAM 191)
Victor Rabinowitz Papers (TAM 123)
Scope and Content Note
This unprocessed collection of records created or collected by the Center for Constitutional Rights (CCR) consists of correspondence, political ephemera, newspaper clippings, websites, research files, audiovisual and digital media, and legal documents, including briefs, motions, and trial transcripts documenting the organization's legal advocacy.
Other Finding Aids
The inventories used to create the container list below were not exhaustive; please contact Special Collections to for information about more comprehensive inventories.
Civil rights -- United States.; Legal services -- New York (State) -- New York.; Lawyers -- Political activity.; Civil rights -- New York (State) -- New York.
- New York Public Library Schomburg Accession
  - Morton Sobell vs. US, 1959-1967 (Box 1)
  - Willie Seals, 1960-1970 (Box 2)
  - Willie Seals v. Alabama, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Council of Federated Organizations, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Kunstler-Kinoy, 1964-1968 (Box 5)
  - State of North Carolina vs. Mae Mallory, et al, 1964-1967 (Box 6)
  - Mississippi v. John Slater, Rupert Crawford, et al, 1961-1965 (Box 7)
  - Misc. Civil Rights cases, 1964-1966 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Files, 1964-1968 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Files (briefs, opinions, etc), undated (Box 10)
  - Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party Challenge, 1965 (Box 11)
  - Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party Challenge, 1965-1966 (Box 12)
  - Jack Ruby, 1965-1966 (Box 13)
  - Fannie Lou Hamer v. Campbell, 1966-1969 (Box 14)
  - Miles v. Dixon, 1966 (Box 15)
  - #149 – Baines v. City of Danville, 1966 (Box 16)
  - #118: Stamler v. Willis, 1965 (Box 17)
  - H. Rap Brown Louisiana case, 1967-1970 (Box 18)
  - Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, undated (Box 19)
  - Fannie Lou Hamer v. Sam Ely, 1967 (Box 20)
  - U.S. v. Reies Lopez Tijerina, 1967 (Box 21)
  - U.S. v. Reies Lopez Tijerina, 1967 (Box 22)
  - Julius Hobson v. Civil Service Commission, 1967 (Box 23)
  - Hobson v. Hansen; Powell v. McCormack; Kinoy v. District of Columbia, undated (Box 24)
  - State of New Jersey vs. George Merritt, et al, 1967-1980 (Box 25)
  - New Jersey vs. Funicello, 1967 (Box 26)
  - Grand Jury Indictment of John P. Tillman, et al, 1967 (Box 27)
  - Frederick Brooks v. Nashville, Tennessee, 1967 (Box 28)
  - #169 – Floyd Nichols v. Vance, 1967 (Box 29)
  - #159 – Warren v. Grove, 1968 (Box 30)
  - H. Rap Brown, 1968 (Box 31)
  - Chicago Democratic National Convention, 1968 (Box 32)
  - US v. Dellinger, 1968 (Box 33)
  - US v. Dellinger, 1968-1974 (Box 34)
  - US v. Dellinger, et al, 1968 (Box 35)
  - US v. Dellinger, et al, 1968 (Box 36)
  - #271 – US v. Dellinger, 1968 (Box 37)
  - Anderson v. Sills, 1968 (Box 38)
  - Ocean Hill-Brownsville, 1968-1969 (Box 39)
  - Ocean Hill-Brownsville, 1968-1969 (Box 40)
  - Rev. C. Herbert Oliver v. Bernard Donovan, et al, 1968 (Box 41)
  - #241 – Irvin Lee "Jack" Dawkins v. William Green, et al, 1968 (Box 42)
  - State of New Jersey v. Brandon, Merritt, et al, 1968 (Box 43)
  - New Jersey v. Merritt, 1968 (Box 44)
  - #179 – Morris Grossner v. Columbia University, 1968 (Box 45)
  - #251 – US v. Berrigan, et al, 1968 (Box 46)
  - #7 – Lawrence Gay Liberation Movement vs. University of Kansas, 1972 (Box 47)
  - Ocean Hill-Brownsville, 1968 (Box 48)
  - I.S. 201 v. New York City Board of Education, 1968 (Box 49)
  - Jerry Rubin bureau file, 1970 (Box 50)
  - US v. Dellinger, 1969 (Box 51)
  - US v. Dellinger, 1969 (Box 52)
  - US v. Dellinger, 1969 (Box 53)
  - US v. Dellinger, 1969 (Box 54)
  - US v. Dellinger, et al, 1969-1970 (Box 55)
  - US v. Dellinger, et al, 1969-1970 (Box 56)
  - Dellinger v. Mitchell, 1969-1970 (Box 57)
  - US v. Dellinger, 1969 (Box 58)
  - In the matter of Dellinger, 1969-1972, 1979-1980 (Box 59)
  - US vs. George Jurich et al, 1969 (Box 60)
  - #239 – US v. Linda Forrest, Barbara Webster, et al, #240 - US v. Cotton, et al, 1969 (Box 61)
  - #227 – Texas v. Marjorie Haile, Mark Rudd, et al, 1969 (Box 62)
  - #252 – Wesley Freeman v. George Schultz, et al, 1969 (Box 63)
  - COINTELPRO:, undated (Box 64)
  - #260 – Katherin Czarnick v. Robert Morgenthau, 1969-1970 (Box 65)
  - Reies Lopez Tijerina, 1967 (Box 66)
  - Segall v. Jacobson - Some components RESTRICTED, undated (Box 67)
  - H. Rap Brown, 1970 (Box 68)
  - #299 - George Jackson v. California, #300 - US v. Maynard, 1970 (Box 69)
  - Eqbal Ahmad, 1970 (Box 70)
  - Liberation News Service v. James Eastland, 1970 (Box 71)
  - New Jersey vs. George Merritt, 1970-1977 (Box 72)
  - U.S. v. Dellinger, et al, 1970 (Box 73)
  - US v. Dellinger, 1970-1973 (Box 74)
  - #310 – Parents and Voters v. District 5 in Harlem, 1970 (Box 75)
  - #322 – Berrigan v. Norton, prison warden, 1974 (Box 76)
  - Ohio State University cases, 1970 (Box 77)
  - #1 – Frank W. Oliver v. Edwin Robson, et al, 1970 (Box 78)
  - #291-A – Jeffrey Segal vs. George Reed, et al, US Board of Parole, 1970 (Box 79)
  - #293 – US Servicemen's Fund v. James Eastland, et al, 1970 (Box 80)
  - Eqbal Ahmad, et al, 1971 (Box 81)
  - U.S. v. Ahmad, et al, 1971 (Box 82)
  - Attica, 1971 (Box 83)
  - Attica, 1971-1972 (Box 84)
  - H. Rap Brown v. USA, 1972-1973 (Box 85)
  - H. Rap Brown, 1971-1976 (Box 86)
  - People of New York v. Wallace Baker, Ronald Felder, William Craig and Walter Thomas, 1971 (Box 87)
  - Judge Bruce Wright v. Police Benevolent Association, 1971 (Box 88)
  - People v. Cruz, 1971 (Box 89)
  - Michael Ratner files, 1971-1973 (Box 90)
  - Monell v. Department of Social Services, New York, 1971-1981 (Box 91)
  - #339 – US v. Private Scott McNeil, 1971 (Box 92)
  - #261 – State of New York v. Preston Lay, et al, 1971 (Box 93)
  - #318 – U.S. Servicemen Fund v. Melvin Laird, 1970-1971 (Box 94)
  - Mildred F. Brown v. Richard Nixon, et al, 1971 (Box 95)
  - New York vs. John Hill and Charles Pernasilice, 1972 (Box 96)
  - US v. Eqbal Ahmad, et al, 1972 (Box 97)
  - U.S. vs. John Briggs, et al; Briggs v. Goodwin, 1972-1973 (Box 98)
  - "Gainesville 8", 1972 (Box 99)
  - "Gainesville 8", 1972 (Box 100)
  - VVAW, 1972-1973 (Box 101)
  - US v. Briggs, et al, 1972 (Box 102)
  - Wallace v. Kern, 1972-1974 (Box 103)
  - Wallace v. Kern, 1972-1974 (Box 104)
  - Wallace v. Kern, 1972 (Box 105)
  - Wallace v. Kern, et al, 1972 (Box 106)
  - Grand Jury indictment against Cobleskill demonstrators, 1972 (Box 107)
  - Kinoy vs. Mitchell, 1975 (Box 108)
  - #432 – US v. Delfin Ramos, 1975-1976 (Box 109)
  - US v. Jose Torres and Ruben Vega y Merced., undated (Box 110)
  - WBAI-FM Grand Jury subpoena, 1973 (Box 111)
  - #354 – People v. Carlos Feliciano, 1972 (Box 112)
  - H. Rap Brown, 1973 (Box 113)
  - H. Rap Brown, 1973 (Box 114)
  - Wallace v. Kern, 1973-1974 (Box 115)
  - Wallace v. Kern, 1973-1975 (Box 116)
  - Wallace v. Kern, 1973 (Box 117)
  - Chicago 7 conspiracy case, 1973 (Box 118)
  - Chicago 7 conspiracy case, 1973 (Box 119)
  - Dellinger v. Mitchell, 1973 (Box 120)
  - VVAW, 1973 (Box 121)
  - Briggs v. Goodwin, 1973 (Box 122)
  - US vs. Briggs, Camil, et al, 1973 (Box 123)
  - Government of the Virgin Islands v. Beaumont Gereau, et al, 1973 (Box 124)
  - Virgin Islands v. Gereau, et al, 1973 (Box 125)
  - #404 – Philip and Daniel Berrigan v. Maurice Sigler, Chairman, US Board of Parole, et al, 1973 (Box 126)
  - #405 – Kathie Mae Andrews v. Drew Municipal School District, 1973 (Box 127)
  - U.S. v. Banks and Means, 1974-1977 (Box 128)
  - US v. Zimmerman, 1974 (Box 129)
  - Daniel Taylor v. Kentucky Bar Association, 1974 (Box 130)
  - Arthur F. Turco, Jr. vs. Monroe County Association, 1974 (Box 131)
  - Arthur Turco v. Monroe County Bar Association, 1974 (Box 132)
  - Willie Aikens v. I.W. Abel, et al, 1974 (Box 133)
  - #426 – U.S. v. Allegheny Ludlum Industries, 1974-1976 (Box 134)
  - #444-A – In Re Burns, et al (BLA Grand Jury), 1975 (Box 135)
  - #425 – State of New York v. Danny White, 1975-1979 (Box 136)
  - Dellinger v. John Mitchell - Briefs, 1975-1979 (Box 137)
  - Grand Jury cases, 1975 (Box 138)
  - #463 – In the Matter of Phillip Shinnick, 1976-1977 (Box 139)
  - Nguyen Da Yen v. Kissinger et al, 1975-1976 (Box 140)
  - Nguyen Da Yen v. Henry Kissinger, 1975-1979 (Box 141)
  - Vietnam Babylift Operation, 1976-1977 (Box 142)
  - RESTRICTED - Vietnam Babylift Operation, 1976-1977 (Box 143)
  - Carmen Bruno v. Robert McGuire et al, 1976 (Box 144)
  - Carmen Bruno v. Michael Codd, NYPD, 1976 (Box 145)
  - Carmen Bruno v. Michael Codd, NYPD, 1976 (Box 146)
  - Cora McRae v. Joseph Califano, 1976 (Box 147)
  - Philip Kent Shinnick, 1976-1977 (Box 148)
  - Roysworth Grant v. Bethlehem Steel Corporation, et al, 1976-1980 (Box 149)
  - United States v. Union Nacional de Trabajadores, 1976 (Box 150)
  - Judith Clavir, Stewart Albert, William Kunstler and Margaret Ratner v. Clarence Kelly, 1977 (Box 151)
  - FBI File on William Kunstler., undated (Box 152)
  - #501 – In the Matter of Jerry Paul, 1977-1980 (Box 153)
  - Middlesex County Ethics Committee v. Garden State Bar Association, et al, 1978-1982 (Box 154)
  - US v. Rosado, 1978-1982 (Box 155)
  - Cerro Maravilla Grand Jury case, 1978 (Box 156)
  - US v. Bonilla et al, 1979 (Box 157)
  - Hope Punnett v. Carter, 1979 (Box 158)
  - Hope Punnett v. Carter, 1979 (Box 159)
  - Briggs v. Goodwin, 1979-1980 (Box 160)
  - Briggs v. Goodwin, 1979-1980 (Box 161)
  - Briggs v. Goodwin, 1979-1980 (Box 162)
  - Briggs v. Goodwin, 1979-1980 (Box 163)
  - Briggs v. Goodwin, 1979-1980 (Box 164)
  - Briggs v. Goodwin, 1979-1980 (Box 165)
  - Cruz v. Alexander, 1979-1980 (Box 166)
  - Roysworth Grant v. Bethlehem Steel Corporation, 1979 (Box 167)
  - U.S. v. Dellinger, 1979-1981 (Box 168)
  - U.S. v. Dellinger, et al., undated (Box 169)
  - US v. Dellinger, et al., undated (Box 170)
  - State of New Jersey v. George Merritt, Jr., 1980 (Box 171)
  - Julius Hobson v. Jerry Wilson, et al, 1982 (Box 172)
  - Julius Hobson v. Jerry Wilson, et al, 1983 (Box 173)
  - RESTRICTED - #278 – William Meacham v. Univ. of Texas Board of Regents, 1969 (Box 174)
  - Fannie Crumsey v. Justice Knights of the Ku Klux Klan, 1980 (Box 175)
    - William Church Press Conference, 1980; cuid36395 (Box 175, Audiocassette cuid36395)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Duration: 53 minutes
    - Comp #31507 - Radiotape on 416 on E. 9th St., April 19, 1980; cuid36855 (Box 175, Audiocassette cuid36855)
      Duration: 17 minutes
    - Statement of Bill Church / Sgt. Kuykendall, April 19, 1980; cuid36856 (Box 175, Audiocassette cuid36856)
      Duration: 8 minutes
    - Statement of Larry Payne, April 20, 1980; cuid36857 (Box 175, Audiocassette cuid36857)
      Duration: 22 minutes
  - # 151 - Dombrowski v. Sourwine, 1967 (Box 176)
  - Smith v. University of Tennessee, 1969 (Box 177)
  - #383 - US v. Jose Torres Cruz and Ruben Alberta Vega y Merced., undated (Box 178)
  - RESTRICTED FILES, Kunstler-Kinoy, 1964-1970s (Box 179)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access to Box 179 is restricted.
  - RESTRICTED - East NY Mental Health Clinic, 1983 (Box 180)
    Access to Box 180 is restricted.
  - RESTRICTED - East New York Mental Health Clinic, 1983 (Box 181)
    Access to Box 181 is restricted.
  - RESTRICTED - LAWYERS CORRESPONDENCE RE: MORTON SOBELL, ETC, undated (Box 182)
    Access to Box 182 is restricted.
  - RESTRICTED - PATIENT RECORDS - East New York Mental Health Clinic, 1983 (Box 183)
    Access to Box 183 is restricted.
  - US v. Dellinger, 1969 (Box 184)
  - Bobby Seale - Appeals case, 1969 (Box 247)
- Series: Archived Websites, February 2007-ongoing; 7 websites in 7 archived websites.
  Scope and Content Note
  Capture of the Center for Constitutional Rights (CCR) website began in 2007 at http://www.ccr-ny.org/v2/home.asp. The website contained news, press releases, pamphlets, and fact sheets from the organization. It also includes education and outreach information on police brutality, alternatives to incarceration, prison phone contract monopolies, reparations, and the Movement Support Resource Center. Their legal programs in 2007 focused on international human rights, government misconduct, racial and economic justice, September 11, Cuba travel ban, corporate accountability, and Guantánamo Bay. In 2008, the organization's URL changed to http://www.ccrjustice.org/. The website then included a legal glossary, their newsletter and press releases, press about CCR, and their legal docket on issues such as illegal dentention and Guantánamo, surveillance and attacks on dissent, criminal justice and mass incarceration, corporate human rights abuse, government abuse of power, racial, gender, and economic justice, and international law and accountability. In 2015, the website went through another redeisgn and expanded their case load to cases related to abusive immigration practices, corporate human rights abuses, criminalizing disset, discrimatory policiting, drone killings, government surveillance, Guantánamo Bay, LGBTQIA+ persecution, mass incarceration, Muslim profiling, Palestinian solidarity, racial injustice, sexual and gender-based violence, and torture, war crimes, and militarism. The website at the time also highlights the Bertha Justice Institute, an arm of CCR to support early career lawyers and legal workers. In 2015, they also launched their blog, the Daily Outrage. In 2018, CCR launched the Activist Files, a podcast that features stories of activists, lawyers, and artists fighting for justice. The website also shifted to highlighting more ways to get involved with CCR, through internships, fellowships, volunteering, job opportunities, events, fact sheets, reports, client profiles, testimony, and advocacy videos.
  FOIA Basics for Activists is a resource guide created by the Center for Constitutional Rights to assist activists, organizers, and social movements in filing Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests to aid their ongoing campaigns and work. It is primarily focused on using FOIA to file requests with federal agencies like the FBI or Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE). It also includes case studies annotated examples, as well as a PDF of the guide.
  If An Agent Knocks is a pamphlet created by the Center for Constitutional Rights to to provide advice to activists likely to be targeted by FBI or other federal agents who have a history of targeting radical and progressive movements. This is the 2020 update to the original 1989 guide and includes more information for non-US citizens.
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
  Accruals
  New site crawls are accrued semiannually.
  During 2020, crawls were increased to monthly accruals.
  Appraisal
  Robots.txt (a piece of code designed to limit crawler activity within a website) was ignored with the permission of the content owner.
  Crawl was limited to domains and subdomains of ccrjustice.org in order to remain within the collection scope and data constraints.